<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3161 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3161.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3280 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5378 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6962 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6962.xml">
]>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" updates="3161" category="std" submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-intesigroup-DLTS-01">
<front>
  <title abbrev="DLTS">Distributed Ledger Time-Stamp</title>
  <author fullname="Emanuele Cisbani" surname="Cisbani" initials="E.">
    <organization>Intesi Group</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Via Torino 48</street>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <code>20123</code>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+39 026 760 641</phone>
      <email>ecisbani@intesigroup.com</email>
      <uri>https://www.intesigroup.com</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Daniele Ribaudo" surname="Ribaudo" initials="D.">
    <organization>Intesi Group</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Via Torino 48</street>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <code>20123</code>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+39 026 760 641</phone>
      <email>dribaudo@intesigroup.com</email>
      <uri>https://www.intesigroup.com</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Giuseppe Damiano" surname="Damiano" initials="G.">
    <organization>Intesi Group</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Via Torino 48</street>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <code>20123</code>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+39 026 760 641</phone>
      <email>dribaudo@intesigroup.com</email>
      <uri>https://www.intesigroup.com</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <date day="13" month="January" year="2020"/>
  <area>Internet</area>

<abstract>
  <t>This document provides a standard to extend Time-Stamp Tokens
with Time Attestations recorded on Distributed Ledgers</t>
</abstract>
</front><middle>
<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction"><t>Attesting that a file existed prior to a specific point in time can be useful to:</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>prove when an agreement was signed, if it is disputed</t>
    <t>validate a signature after a revocation occurred</t>
    <t>prove the ownership for copyright</t>
    <t>grant record Integrity</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>A Time-Stamp Token (TST) provided by a Time-Stamp Authority (TSA) compliant with <xref target="RFC3161"/>
can be based on an accurate time source linked to Coordinated Universal Time,
and can be very precise - it can proves the existence also at the second or less.
It is a so consolidated standard that - for example - the European Union
enforced his usage with legal effect by <xref target="eIDAS"/> Regulation,
<xref target="ETSI.EN.319.422"/> European Standard and <xref target="ETSI.TS.101.861"/> Technical Specification.</t>
<t>In a deep comparation of Time Stamping Schemes conducted in 2001 by Masashi Une <xref target="IMES"/>,
PKI TSA has been evaluated one of the the most desirables with respect to security against
alteration of a time stamp.</t>
<t>The integrity of the timestamping process that is inevitably bound to the integrity of the TSA
gave rise anyway to other proposals like <xref target="ANSI.X9.95"/> and <xref target="ISO.IEC.18014-4"/>.</t>
<t>Furthermore a TSA TST can be validated for a limited time - usually no more than 20 years -
for technical reasons - like the TSA certificates expiration -
and for economic reasons - like the cost of providing the validation service by TSA.</t>
<t>This situation gave rise also to some solutions <xref target="ETSI.TS.102.778-4"/> aimed at mitigating
the issue by extending the validity of TSA timestamps.</t>
<t>Distributed Ledgers <xref target="UK-GCSA"/> security is based on hashes of data timestamped and widely published.
Each timestamp includes the previous timestamp in its hash, forming a chain,
with each additional timestamp reinforcing the ones before it.</t>
<t>The advantage of a Distributed Ledger Attestation (DLA) relies on the resilience
of the distributed system and the overall design aiming to survive perpetually.</t>
<t>Based on a distributed trust scheme, a Distributed Ledger significantly increase
security as already noted by Haber and Stornetta in 1991 <xref target="HaberStornetta"/>.</t>
<t>In the case of a permissioned DL, security could be enhanced by an authoritative network of trust.
While in the case of a permissionless DL security is granted by the economic incentive of nodes
<xref target="Nakamoto"/>.</t>
<t>On the other hand a DLA is not yet a standard. Furthermore a DLA
is as less precise - it proves the existence at a specific hour or day - as bigger and
secure is the network: because distributed nodes need time to reach consensus.</t>
<t>Since a DLA result as a complementary element to provide a long-term
validity to TST - the aim of this specification is to provide an extension
of the Time-Stamp Token for Distributed Ledger Attestations (DLA).</t></section>
<section anchor="conventions" title="Terms and Definitions"><t>The key words "<spanx style="strong">MUST</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">MUST NOT</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">REQUIRED</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">SHALL</spanx>",
"<spanx style="strong">SHALL NOT</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">SHOULD</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">SHOULD NOT</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">RECOMMENDED</spanx>",
"<spanx style="strong">NOT RECOMMENDED</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">MAY</spanx>", and "<spanx style="strong">OPTIONAL</spanx>" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
<xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
all capitals, as shown here.</t>
<t>This document also refers to the following terms and
definitions:</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Public Key Infrastructure"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3280"/></t>
    <t hangText="Trusted Tirth Party"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3161"/></t>
    <t hangText="Time-Stamp Authority"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3161"/></t>
    <t hangText="Time-Stamp Token"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3161"/></t>
    <t hangText="Distributed Ledger"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined by UK Government Chief Scientific Adviser <xref target="UK-GCSA"/>
"A distributed ledger is essentially an asset database that can be shared across
a network of multiple sites, geographies or institutions. All participants within
a network can have their own identical copy of the ledger. Any changes to the
ledger are reflected in all copies in minutes, or in some cases, seconds. The
assets can be financial, legal, physical or electronic. The security and accuracy
of the assets stored in the ledger are maintained cryptographically through the
use of &#8216;keys&#8217; and signatures to control who can do what within the shared ledger.
Entries can also be updated by one, some or all of the participants, according to
rules agreed by the network".</t>
    <t hangText="Merkle Tree"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="Merkle"/>, <xref target="CrosbyWallach"/> andSection 2.1 of <xref target="RFC6962"/></t>
    <t hangText="Aggregation Server"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A server providing the aggregation in a Merke Tree of digests to be timestamped.
Digests submitted for aggregation are added to a list periodically combined
into a single Merkle Tree. Then the digest at the root of that tree is timestamped
on a Distributed Ledger.</t>
    <t hangText="Distributed Ledger Attestation"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A Distributed Ledger (Timestamping) Attestation is a proof or a promise of timestamping
in a precise Distributed Ledger.</t>
    <t hangText="Calendar"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A calendar is simply a collection of Distributed Ledger Attestations.</t>
    <t hangText="Calendar Server"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A server providing remote access to a collection of Distributed Ledger Attestation.</t>
    <t hangText="OpenTimestamps"><vspace blankLines="0"/>An open source software acting as aggregation and calendar server to timestamp
on the Bitcoin Distributed Ledger <xref target="OTS"/>.</t>
  </list>
</t></section>
<section anchor="symbols" title="Symbols And Abbreviations">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="PKI"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Public Key Infrastructure</t>
    <t hangText="TTP"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Trusted Third Party</t>
    <t hangText="TSA"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Time-Stamp Authority</t>
    <t hangText="TST"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Time-Stamp Token</t>
    <t hangText="DL"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Distributed Ledger</t>
    <t hangText="DLA"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Distributed Ledger Attestation</t>
    <t hangText="OTS"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A Digital Ledger Attestation provided by an OpenTimestamps Calendar Server</t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="main" title="DL Attestation"><t>A Digital Ledger can be viewed as an untrusted logger, serving a number of
clients who wish to store their events in the log, and
kept honest by a number of auditors who will challenge
the logger to prove its correct behavior <xref target="CrosbyWallach"/>.</t>
<t>A Merkle Tree data structure allow to accomplish this very efficently aggregating
many requests and submitting to the log periodically just the root digest of the tree.
This log is built as an hash chain (aka blockchain) of small blocks of data.
With this conditions the entire chain can be shared and mantained
by a large number of nodes, becoming a distributed system.</t>
<t>In a permissioned DL the number of nodes can be small enought to permit a quick
syncronization to reach the consensus about the state of the chain.
Instead in a permissionless DL the large number of nodes introduces a relevant delay
to reach the consensus.</t>
<t>In the case of Bitcoin the consensus is reached statistically.
Usually in an elapsed mean time of one hour six new blocks are added to the chain.
A block of data that has been added before the last six blocks
is considered practically immutable.
This is motivated by the high computational power that would be required to rewrite the chain.</t>
<t>As a result of this scenario the time elapsed - from the request of aggregation of a digest
to the proof consolidated inside the DL - could amount to more than one hour.</t>
<t>This is the motivation to distinguish from a <spanx style="strong">promise</spanx> of attestation and a <spanx style="strong">proof</spanx> of attestation.
An Aggregation Server generally can provide only a promise to timestamping the digest of the client
in the DL. After the aggregation is completed and the root hash of the Merkle Tree has been
recorded in a block of the chain, the promise is still not yet comnfirmed,</t>
<t>Only when the consensus on that block is reached - statistically, in the Bitcoin case - then
the attestation could be consideed a proof, stored and provided by a Calendar Server.</t>
<t>For simplicity of implementation, the Aggregation and the Calendar Server can be a uniq instance.</t>
<t>The DLA data structure is out of scope of this specification. Any Calendar Server can define his application protocol and data structure. For this specification the DLA is considered as pure data.</t>
<section anchor="_dl_extension" title="DL Extension"><t>A DL Extension is a data structure included in a TST
using the extensions field defined in Section 2.4.1 of <xref target="RFC3161"/>.</t>
<t>A DL Extension SHALL contain:</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>an OID registered at IANA that uniquely identify the Calendar protocol used</t>
    <t>at least one Calendar Token</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>A DL Extensionn MAY contain also a secondary TST previously obtained.</t>
<t>If there is no a secondary TST, the digest of the DLA is
the same data that will be signed by the TSA without the Calendar Tokenitself.</t>
<t>If there is a secondary TST it is also the digest of the Calendar Token.</t>
<t>A Calendar Token SHALL contain:</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>the version of the DLA</t>
    <t>at least one DLA, that is a timestamping promise OR a timestamp proof</t>
    <t>a string that uniquely identify the DL used by the Calendar Server</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>A Calendar Token MAY contain for each DLA that is a promise
the URI to a document defining the promise policies.</t></section></section>
<section anchor="_opentimestamps" title="OpenTimestamps"><t>It has to be expressly clarified that this specification does not intend to be restricted
to the Bitcoin and OpenTimestamps implementations of DL and Calendar general solutions.
It will just be taken as the starting point for future enhancements and evolutive proposal.</t>
<t>We simply considered that:</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>Bitcoin is the first DL implementation and it is still working since January 2009</t>
    <t>Bitcoin is a permissionless DL, with a significant delay necessary to reach a consensus,
so a standard made to fit for it will be more general and easly usable also for others DL,
also permissioned, eventually providing the proof syncronously, and so not requiring a promise</t>
    <t>the OpenTimestamps software is licensed with the GNU LGPL Version 3, the server is written in python
and clients are available in python, java, javascript and rust</t>
    <t>OpenTimestamps is a proven working solution timestamping on the Bitcoin DL</t>
    <t>OpenTimestamps is potentially DL-agnostic, in fact an experimental version stamping
on the Ethereum DL has been arount for a while</t>
    <t>OpenTimestamps Calendars are currently available for free to the public thanks to donors</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>For all this reasons the choice of Bitcoin as DL and OpenTimestamps as Calendar seem
the favourite example do define an open standard of DL Attestation extending TST validity.</t>
<section anchor="_ots_extension" title="OTS Extension"><t>Il timestamp di tipo opentimestamps (basato su blockchain) dovr&#224; essere generato
tramite l&#8217;utilizzo di un calendar server e inserito come estensione non critica
all&#8217;interno di un timestamp che segue lo standard <xref target="RFC3161"/>.</t>
<t>L&#8217;aggiunta dell&#8217;estensione non critica rende il timestamp finale retro-compatibile
con i software di verifica attualmente disponibili.</t>
<t>L&#8217;estensione deve rispettare le indicazioni riportate in <xref target="RFC3161"/> e Section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC3280"/>.</t>
<t>Gli OID delle nuove estensioni avranno la seguente radice:</t>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
id-ce-opentimestamps   OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-ce 99 }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<t>dove id-ce identifica la radice delle estensioni standard vedi <xref target="RFC3280"/>.</t></section>
<section anchor="_ots_promise" title="OTS Promise"><t>Questa estensione rappresenta la &#8220;promessa&#8221; restituita dal calendar server in risposta alla richiesta di marcatura di un hash. Di seguito &#232; riportata la struttura ASN.1:</t>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
id-ce-opentimestamps-promise OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= {
    id-ce-opentimestamps 1 }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
Promise ::= SEQUENCE {
    version          [0] INTEGER,
    otsPromise       [1] OtsPromise }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
OtsPromise ::= OCTET STRING
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<section anchor="_ots_proof" title="OTS Proof"><t>Questa estensione rappresenta la &#8220;prova&#8221; restituita dal calendar server in risposta alla richiesta di upgrade di una promessa precedentemente ricevuta. Di seguito &#232; riportata la struttura ASN.1:</t>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
id-ce-opentimestamps-proof OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= {
    id-ce-opentimestamps 2 }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
Proof ::= SEQUENCE {
      version        [0] INTEGER,
      otsProof       [1] OtsProof,
      blockchain     [2] UTF8String }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
OtsProof ::= OCTET STRING
]]></artwork>
</figure></section></section>
<section anchor="code-snippets" title="Code snippets">
  <t>Code snippets should be wrapped with <spanx style="verb">&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;</spanx> and
<spanx style="verb">&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;</spanx> blocks, as required by the IETF Trust Legal
Provisions (TLP) <xref target="IETF.TLP"/> (Section 4) specified in <xref target="RFC5378"/>.</t>
</section></section>
<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations"><t>Any security considerations should be placed here.</t>
<t>As described in <xref target="main"/> (here&#8217;s how you refer a local anchor),
local tools have to be installed before the document template
can be built.</t>
<t>Running of these local tools <spanx style="strong">MAY</spanx> produce unintended side
effects that impact security. For example</t>
<texttable suppress-title="false" style="full">
  <ttcol align="left">Security issue</ttcol>
  <ttcol align="left">Discussed in</ttcol>
  <c>Confidentiality</c>
  <c>Section 2.1.1 of <xref target="RFC3552"/></c>
  <c>Data Integrity</c>
  <c>Section 2.1.2 of <xref target="RFC3552"/></c>
  <c>Non-Repudiation</c>
  <c>Section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC3552"/></c>
</texttable></section>
<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations"><t>This document does not require any action by IANA.</t>
<t>But if it does, such as proposing changes to IANA registries,
please include them here.</t></section>
</middle><back>
<references title="Normative References">
  &RFC2119;
  &RFC3161;
  &RFC8174;
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
  <reference anchor="ANSI.X9.95" target="https://webstore.ansi.org/Standards/ASCX9/ANSIX9952005">
  <front>
    <title>
        Trusted Time Stamp Management And Security
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization>
      American National Standards Institute (ANSI)
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>
            1899 L Street, NW
          </street>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://ansi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2005"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="CrosbyWallach" target="http://static.usenix.org/event/sec09/tech/full_papers/crosby.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Efficient Data Structures for Tamper-Evident Logging</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Crosby" fullname="Scott A. Crosby">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Wallach" fullname="Dan S. Wallach">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date year="2009" month="August"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 18th USENIX Security Symposium," value="Montreal"/>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ETSI.EN.319.422" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_en/319400_319499/319422/01.01.01_60/en_319422v010101p.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
    Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI);
    Time-stamping protocol and time-stamp token profiles
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization> European Telecommunications Standards Institute </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Route des Lucioles</street>
          <city>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.etsi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ETSI.TS.101.861" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/101800_101899/101861/01.04.01_60/ts_101861v010401p.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI);
Time stamping profile</title>
    <author>
      <organization> European Telecommunications Standards Institute </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Route des Lucioles</street>
          <city>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.etsi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ETSI.TS.102.778-4" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102700_102799/10277804/01.01.02_60/ts_10277804v010102p.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI);
        PDF Advanced Electronic Signature Profiles;
        Part 4: PAdES Long Term - PAdES-LTV Profile
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization> European Telecommunications Standards Institute </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Route des Lucioles</street>
          <city>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.etsi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2009"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="HaberStornetta" target="https://www.anf.es/pdf/Haber_Stornetta.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        How to Time-Stamp a Digital Document
    </title>
    <author fullname="Stuart Haber">
    </author>
    <author fullname="W. Scott Stornetta">
    </author>
    <date year="1991"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="IETF.TLP" target="https://trustee.ietf.org/trust-legal-provisions.html">
  <front>
  <title>IETF Trust Legal Provisions (TLP)</title>
  <author>
    <organization>IETF</organization>
  </author>
  <date month="April" day="12" year="2018"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="IMES" target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.23.7486">
  <front>
    <title>
        The Security Evaluation of Time Stamping Schemes: The Present Situation and Studies (2001)
    </title>
    <author fullname="Masashi Une">
    <organization>
    INSTITUTE FOR MONETARY AND ECONOMIC STUDIES - BANK OF JAPAN
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2001"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ISO.IEC.18014-4" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/59934.html">
  <front>
    <title>
    Information technology - Security techniques -
    Time-stamping services - Part 4: Traceability of time sources
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization> International Organization for Standardization </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Chemin de Blandonnet 8</street>
          <city>Vernier, Geneva</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.iso.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="Merkle" target="http://www.merkle.com/papers/Thesis1979.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Secrecy, authentication, and public-key systems - Technical Report No. 1979-1
    </title>
    <author fullname="Ralph Charles Merkle">
    <organization>
    Stanford Electronics Laboratories, Department of Electrical Engeneering, Stanford University, Stanford. CA 94305
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="1979"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="Nakamoto" target="https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Bitcoin: A Peer-to-Peer Electronic Cash System
    </title>
    <author fullname="Satoshi Nakamoto">
    </author>
    <date day="31" month="October" year="2008"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="OTS" target="https://petertodd.org/2016/opentimestamps-announcement">
  <front>
    <title>
        OpenTimestamps: Scalable, Trust-Minimized, Distributed Timestamping with Bitcoin
    </title>
    <author fullname="Peter Todd">
    </author>
    <date day="15" month="September" year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="UK-GCSA" target="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/492972/gs-16-1-distributed-ledger-technology.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Distributed Ledger Technology: beyond block chain
    </title>
    <author>
    <organization>
    UK Government Chief Scientific Adviser
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="eIDAS" target="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32014R0910=EN">
  <front>
    <title>
        Regulation (EU) No 910/2014
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization>
        The European Parliament And The Council Of The European Union
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>60 rue Wiertz / Wiertzstraat 60</street>
          <city> Bruxelles</city>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://europarl.europa.eu</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="23" month="July" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  &RFC3280;
  &RFC3552;
  &RFC5378;
  &RFC6962;
</references>
</back>
</rfc>
