<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3161 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3161.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5378 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6962 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6962.xml">
]>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" updates="3161" category="std" submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-intesigroup-DLTS-00">
<front>
  <title abbrev="DLTS">Distributed Ledger Time-Stamp</title>
  <author fullname="Emanuele Cisbani" surname="Cisbani" initials="E.">
    <organization>Intesi Group</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Via Torino 48</street>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <code>20123</code>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+39 026 760 641</phone>
      <email>ecisbani@intesigroup.com</email>
      <uri>https://www.intesigroup.com</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Daniele Ribaudo" surname="Ribaudo" initials="D.">
    <organization>Intesi Group</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Via Torino 48</street>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <code>20123</code>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+39 026 760 641</phone>
      <email>dribaudo@intesigroup.com</email>
      <uri>https://www.intesigroup.com</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Giuseppe Damiano" surname="Damiano" initials="G.">
    <organization>Intesi Group</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Via Torino 48</street>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <code>20123</code>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+39 026 760 641</phone>
      <email>gdamiano@intesigroup.com</email>
      <uri>https://www.intesigroup.com</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
  <date day="25" month="May" year="2020"/>
  <area>Internet</area>

<abstract><t>This document defines a standard to extend Time Stamp Tokens
with Time Attestations recorded on Distributed Ledgers.</t>
<t>The aim is to provide long-term validity to Time Stamp Tokens,
backward compatible with currently available existing software.</t></abstract>
</front><middle>
<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction"><t>Attesting that a file existed prior to a specific point in time can be useful - for example - to:</t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>prove when an agreement was signed, if it is disputed</t>
    <t>validate a signature after a revocation occurred</t>
    <t>prove the ownership for copyright</t>
    <t>grant record integrity</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>A Time-Stamp Token (TST) provided by a Time-Stamp Authority (TSA) compliant with <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref>
can be based on an accurate time source linked to Coordinated Universal Time,
and can be very precise - it can prove the existence also at the second or less.
It is such a consolidated standard that - for example - the European Union legally
enforced its usage by <xref target="eIDAS">eIDAS Regulation</xref>,
European Standards and Technical Specifications
<xref target="ETSI.EN.319.422"/> <xref target="ETSI.TS.101.861"/>.</t>
<t>In an in-deep appraisal of Time Stamping Schemes conducted in 2001 by Masashi Une <xref target="IMES"/>,
PKI TSA was evaluated as one of the most desirables in term of security against
alteration of a time stamp.</t>
<t>The integrity of the timestamping process that is inevitably bound to the integrity of the TSA
gave rise to other proposals like <xref target="ANSI.X9.95">ANSI X9.95</xref> and <xref target="ISO.IEC.18014-4">ISO/IEC 18014-4</xref>.</t>
<t>Furthermore a TSA TST can be validated for a limited time - usually no longer than 20 years
for technical reasons such as the TSA certificates expiration, or
for economic reasons such as the cost of providing the validation service by TSA.</t>
<t>This situation brought about some solutions <xref target="ETSI.TS.102.778-4"/> aimed at mitigating
the inconvenience by extending the validity of TSA timestamps.</t>
<t>Security of a Distributed Ledger (def. in <xref target="conventions"/>) is based on hashes of data
timestamped and widely published.
Each timestamp includes the previous timestamp in its hash, forming a chain,
with each additional timestamp reinforcing the ones before it.</t>
<t>The advantage of a Distributed Ledger Attestation (DLA) relies on the resilience
of the distributed system and the overall design whose aim is the DL perpetual survival.</t>
<t>Based on a distributed trust scheme, a Distributed Ledger significantly increases
security as already noted by Haber and Stornetta in 1991 <xref target="HaberStornetta"/>.</t>
<t>In the case of a permissioned DL, security is provided by an authoritative network of trust <xref target="Hyperledger"/><xref target="NISTIR_8202"/>,
while in the case of a permissionless DL security is provided by the economic incentive for running full nodes <xref target="Nakamoto"/>.</t>
<t>On the other hand, a DLA is not yet a standard solution.
Furthermore, the bigger the network the less precise the DLA,
because distributed nodes need time to reach consensus.</t>
<t>Since a DLA turns out to be a complementary element providing long-term
validity to TST - the aim of this specification is to allow an extension
of the Time-Stamp Token for Distributed Ledger Attestations (DLA).</t></section>
<section anchor="conventions" title="Terms and Definitions"><t>The key words "<spanx style="strong">MUST</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">MUST NOT</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">REQUIRED</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">SHALL</spanx>",
"<spanx style="strong">SHALL NOT</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">SHOULD</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">SHOULD NOT</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">RECOMMENDED</spanx>",
"<spanx style="strong">NOT RECOMMENDED</spanx>", "<spanx style="strong">MAY</spanx>", and "<spanx style="strong">OPTIONAL</spanx>" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
<xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
all capitals, as shown here.</t>
<t>This document also refers to the following terms and
definitions:</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Public Key Infrastructure"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref></t>
    <t hangText="Trusted Third Party"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref></t>
    <t hangText="Time-Stamp Authority"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref></t>
    <t hangText="Time-Stamp Token"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref></t>
    <t hangText="Distributed Ledger"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Various definitions of blockchain and distributed ledger technology exist,
and some of these stress different technical features.
Given the nature and scope of this document and the lack of definitional
consensus we chose to use the term
as defined by UK Government Chief Scientific Adviser <xref target="UK-GCSA"/>
"A distributed ledger is essentially an asset database that can be shared across
a network of multiple sites, geographies or institutions. All participants within
a network can have their own identical copy of the ledger. Any changes to the
ledger are reflected in all copies in minutes, or in some cases, seconds. The
assets can be financial, legal, physical or electronic. The security and accuracy
of the assets stored in the ledger are maintained cryptographically through the
use of &#8216;keys&#8217; and signatures to control who can do what within the shared ledger.
Entries can also be updated by one, some or all of the participants, according to
rules agreed by the network".</t>
    <t hangText="Merkle Tree"><vspace blankLines="0"/>As defined in <xref target="Merkle"/>, <xref target="CrosbyWallach"/> and Section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC6962">RFC 6962</xref></t>
    <t hangText="Aggregation Server"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A server providing the aggregation of digests to be timestamped in a Merkle Tree.
Digests submitted for aggregation are added to a list periodically combined
into a single Merkle Tree. Then the digest at the root of that tree is timestamped
on a Distributed Ledger.</t>
    <t hangText="Distributed Ledger Attestation"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A Distributed Ledger (Timestamping) Attestation is a proof or a promise of timestamping
in a precise Distributed Ledger.</t>
    <t hangText="Calendar"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A calendar is simply a collection of Distributed Ledger Attestations.</t>
    <t hangText="Calendar Server"><vspace blankLines="0"/>A server providing remote access to a collection of Distributed Ledger Attestations.</t>
  </list>
</t></section>
<section anchor="symbols" title="Symbols And Abbreviations">
  <t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="PKI"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Public Key Infrastructure</t>
    <t hangText="TTP"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Trusted Third Party</t>
    <t hangText="TSA"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Time-Stamp Authority</t>
    <t hangText="TST"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Time-Stamp Token</t>
    <t hangText="DL"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Distributed Ledger</t>
    <t hangText="DLA"><vspace blankLines="0"/>Distributed Ledger Attestation</t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="main" title="DL Attestation"><t>A Digital Ledger can be seen as an untrusted logger - serving a number of
clients who wish to store their events in the log -
kept honest by a number of auditors who will challenge
the logger to prove its correct behaviour <xref target="CrosbyWallach"/>.</t>
<t>A Merkle Tree data structure accomplishes this in a very efficient way by aggregating
many requests and submitting periodically to the log only the root digest of the tree.
This log is built as a hash chain (aka blockchain) of small blocks of data.
Consequently, the entire chain can be shared and maintained
by a large number of nodes, becoming a distributed system.</t>
<t>In a permissioned DL the number of nodes can be small enough to permit a quick
synchronization and reach consensus concerning the state of the chain.
In a permissionless DL the large number of nodes introduces a relevant delay
in order to reach consensus.</t>
<t>In the case of Bitcoin, consensus is reached statistically.
Usually in an average elapsed time of one hour six new blocks are added to the chain.
A block of data that was added before the last six blocks, is considered to be practically immutable.
This is due to the high computational power that would be required to rewrite the chain.</t>
<t>As a result of this scenario the elapsed time - from the request of aggregation of a digest
to the proof consolidated inside the DL, may amount to one hour or more.</t>
<t>This is why we distinguish between a <spanx style="strong">promise</spanx> of attestation and a <spanx style="strong">proof</spanx> of attestation.
Generally, an Aggregation Server provides only a promise to timestamp the client&#8217;s digest
in the DL. However, when the aggregation is completed and the Merkle Tree root hash recorded in a block within the chain, the promise has not yet been confirmed.</t>
<t>Only after reaching consensus on that block can attestation be considered as proof,
and made available by the Calendar Server.</t>
<t>For the sake of simplicity, the Aggregation Server and the Calendar Server
can be implemented as a unique instance.
In this document we will generically refer to a Calendar Server indicating both services.</t>
<t>The DLA data structure is out of scope in this specification document. Any Calendar Server can define his application protocol and data structure. For this specification the DLA is considered as pure data.</t></section>
<section anchor="_dl_time_stamp_extension" title="DL Time-Stamp Extension"><t>A DLA, generated by a Calendar Server, MAY be included
into a TST, using a non critical extension <xref target="RFC3161"/>.</t>
<t>The use of non critical extension is backward compatible with currently available existing software.</t>
<t>The extension MUST be compliant to the specifications described in <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref> and Section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref>.</t>
<t>The new extension MUST have the following root OID:</t>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
id-ce-dlts OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-ce TBD1 }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<t>where id-ce identify the root of standard extensions as described in <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref>.</t>
<section anchor="_promise" title="Promise"><t>This extension contains the promise obtained from a Calendar Server in response to a timestamp request on the DL.
The ASN.1 structure is as follows:</t>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
id-ce-dlts-promise OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-ce-dlts 1 }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
Promise ::= SEQUENCE {
    version          [0] INTEGER,
    dlpromise        [1] DLPromise }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
DLPromise ::= OCTET STRING
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<t>The input data, timestamped by the DLA, SHALL be the hash value of the same data that will be signed by the TSA, without the DL extension itself.</t></section>
<section anchor="_proof" title="Proof"><t>This extension contains the proof obtained from a Calendar Server in response to a timestamp upgrade request of a previously obtained promise.
The ASN.1 structure is as follows:</t>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
id-ce-dlts-proof OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= {
    id-ce-dlts 2 }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
Proof ::= SEQUENCE {
      version        [0] INTEGER,
      dlproof        [1] DLProof,
      blockchain     [2] UTF8String }
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
DLProof ::= OCTET STRING
]]></artwork>
</figure>
<t>Upgrade from a promise to a proof MAY be done requesting a new TST, including
the DL extension containing the promise previously obtained.
When the TSA receives a request containing a DL extension,
and there is a pending promise inside, it MAY request
from the Calendar Server to get the proof and MAY include it in the TST response.</t></section>
<section anchor="_dl_promise_generation_process" title="DL Promise Generation Process"><t>The input to the DL Promise generation process includes the result of
the message digest calculation of the DER encoded TST, without the DL extension.
If the TST contains more extensions, the hash calculation is applied to the DER
encoded TST containing all the extensions with the exclusion of new DL extension itself.</t>
<t>The hash algorithm and hash parameters are the same of the TST signature,
which are included in the final ContentInfo object, as described in Section 2.4.2 of <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref>.</t></section></section>
<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations"><t>Each security consideration described in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC3161">RFC 3161</xref> SHALL be evaluated designing
TSA services that include DL Time-Stamp extensions.</t>
<t>When a TSA executes a request to a Calendar Server the use of a nonce is
RECOMMENDED because using a nonce always allows the client to detect replays.</t>
<t>Safety and reliability of the DL Extension depends on the robustness
of the hash algorithms and on the stability of the DL,
i.e. how expensive or difficult it would be for an attacker to alter the DL.</t></section>
<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>This document does not require any action by IANA.</t>
</section>
</middle><back>
<references title="Normative References">
  &RFC2119;
  &RFC3161;
  &RFC5280;
  &RFC8174;
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
  <reference anchor="ANSI.X9.95" target="https://webstore.ansi.org/Standards/ASCX9/ANSIX9952005">
  <front>
    <title>
        Trusted Time Stamp Management And Security
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization>
      American National Standards Institute (ANSI)
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>
            1899 L Street, NW
          </street>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://ansi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2005"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="CrosbyWallach" target="http://static.usenix.org/event/sec09/tech/full_papers/crosby.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Efficient Data Structures for Tamper-Evident Logging</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Crosby" fullname="Scott A. Crosby">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Wallach" fullname="Dan S. Wallach">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date year="2009" month="August"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 18th USENIX Security Symposium," value="Montreal"/>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ETSI.EN.319.422" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_en/319400_319499/319422/01.01.01_60/en_319422v010101p.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
    Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI);
    Time-stamping protocol and time-stamp token profiles
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization> European Telecommunications Standards Institute </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Route des Lucioles</street>
          <city>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.etsi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ETSI.TS.101.861" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/101800_101899/101861/01.04.01_60/ts_101861v010401p.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI);
Time stamping profile</title>
    <author>
      <organization> European Telecommunications Standards Institute </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Route des Lucioles</street>
          <city>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.etsi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ETSI.TS.102.778-4" target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_ts/102700_102799/10277804/01.01.02_60/ts_10277804v010102p.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Electronic Signatures and Infrastructures (ESI);
        PDF Advanced Electronic Signature Profiles;
        Part 4: PAdES Long Term - PAdES-LTV Profile
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization> European Telecommunications Standards Institute </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Route des Lucioles</street>
          <city>Sophia Antipolis Cedex</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.etsi.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2009"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="HaberStornetta" target="https://www.anf.es/pdf/Haber_Stornetta.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        How to Time-Stamp a Digital Document
    </title>
    <author fullname="Stuart Haber">
    </author>
    <author fullname="W. Scott Stornetta">
    </author>
    <date year="1991"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="Hyperledger" target="https://www.hyperledger.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/08/Hyperledger_Arch_WG_Paper_1_Consensus.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Hyperledger Architecture, Volume 1: Introduction to Hyperledger Business Blockchain Design Philosophy and Consensus
    </title>
    <author>
    <organization>
    The Linux Foundation
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="August" year="2017"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="IETF.TLP" target="https://trustee.ietf.org/trust-legal-provisions.html">
  <front>
  <title>IETF Trust Legal Provisions (TLP)</title>
  <author>
    <organization>IETF</organization>
  </author>
  <date month="April" day="12" year="2018"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="IMES" target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.23.7486">
  <front>
    <title>
        The Security Evaluation of Time Stamping Schemes: The Present Situation and Studies (2001)
    </title>
    <author fullname="Masashi Une">
    <organization>
    INSTITUTE FOR MONETARY AND ECONOMIC STUDIES - BANK OF JAPAN
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2001"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="ISO.IEC.18014-4" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/59934.html">
  <front>
    <title>
    Information technology - Security techniques -
    Time-stamping services - Part 4: Traceability of time sources
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization> International Organization for Standardization </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Chemin de Blandonnet 8</street>
          <city>Vernier, Geneva</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://www.iso.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2015"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="Merkle" target="http://www.merkle.com/papers/Thesis1979.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Secrecy, authentication, and public-key systems - Technical Report No. 1979-1
    </title>
    <author fullname="Ralph Charles Merkle">
    <organization>
    Stanford Electronics Laboratories, Department of Electrical Engeneering, Stanford University, Stanford. CA 94305
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="1979"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="NISTIR_8202" target="https://doi.org/10.6028/NIST.IR.8202">
  <front>
    <title>
        Blockchain Technology Overview
    </title>
    <author fullname="Dylan Yaga">
    <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Peter Mell">
    <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Nik Roby">
    <organization>G2, Inc.</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Karen Scarfone">
    <organization>Scarfone Cybersecurity</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2018"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="Nakamoto" target="https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Bitcoin: A Peer-to-Peer Electronic Cash System
    </title>
    <author fullname="Satoshi Nakamoto">
    </author>
    <date day="31" month="October" year="2008"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="UK-GCSA" target="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/492972/gs-16-1-distributed-ledger-technology.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>
        Distributed Ledger Technology: beyond block chain
    </title>
    <author>
    <organization>
    UK Government Chief Scientific Adviser
    </organization>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  <reference anchor="eIDAS" target="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32014R0910=EN">
  <front>
    <title>
        Regulation (EU) No 910/2014
    </title>
    <author>
      <organization>
        The European Parliament And The Council Of The European Union
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>60 rue Wiertz / Wiertzstraat 60</street>
          <city> Bruxelles</city>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <uri>https://europarl.europa.eu</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="23" month="July" year="2014"/>
  </front>
</reference>
  &RFC3552;
  &RFC5378;
  &RFC6962;
</references>
</back>
</rfc>
